hello everyone welcome to voices with
verviki i'm joined one more time
and paul probably not the last time uh
by my good friend
and colleague uh lehman pascal who has
generated so many wonderful uh dialogues
on voices with raviki so
uh welcome back layman it's good to have
you here again hi john lovely to be here
uh i think last time we've sort of been
thinking about this as a
as my overarching series with some
themed stuff
i'm thinking of the overarching theme as
something like post-metaphysical
spirituality
right so last time we delved into beauty
and we talked last time at the end about
um i guess the transposition of
optimal grip skills into domains like
politics
yes yeah that's a tricky one to think
out so i think we should spend some time
on that
yeah i i i think that's that's a good
topic
it's very pertinent um yeah
we'll have to go carefully because of
course this is a topic that is
fraught with reactivity on people's part
and that reactivity i think has been
exacerbated by
the past few months so how would you
like to begin though
i think if we talk at a high enough
level no one will have any idea what
we're saying and that
i've been trying to think about what i
mean by politics and i suppose in
general i would say it's the art of
um embodied distributed intelligence
it's how we get together
to make decisions about how to be and
that can be
smarter or dumber in a sense and then i
would put that in a
in the context of religion which i would
think of as a super political or
metapolitical approach to
recollecting the skills that build
social integration and coherent
mobilization
spirits across the domains of culture in
any epoch
so i think i i'm i'm
online with you the problem for me is i
have two different conceptions of
politics in my mind the first
is very uh similar to what you said i
have aristotle's notion of
politics as you know remember aristotle
says that
man is inherently a social or a
political
being human beings i should say he was
sexist i've tried not to be
um and uh
i think that broadly is right uh i i i
but i'm reminded of nietzsche's uh uh
uh humorous um and ironic twist on that
aristotle says that in order to live
alone one must be either a god or an
animal but one can be both a philosopher
um
so i wonder where that puts us in this
discussion
but so i think that um i tend to reserve
what
but that definition of politics
i'm not so happy with applying although
i think you're right to use it that way
it has a bonafide heritage i think that
the common sense uh everyday sense of
politics
is much more limited to er than what
aristotle said i think for most people
what politics is about is not something
like
um the systemic management
of distributed in cognition uh within
something like a meta meeting system of
religion
um in fact i i would propose that for
most people
uh myself included nowadays that would
be the word culture
um and and the association to
cultivation
and to cult is readily apparent right
um whereas politics i feel
uh for many people now when they hear
that term they're talking about
the principles of governance so for them
politics the locus of politics is more
properly
the state as opposed to the culture
now that might be something you want to
challenge and but i'm just bringing that
up
as you know i think there's two senses
of the word politics
the one that i think you're invoking is
a bona fide one and like i said it's
clearly found in aristotle
but i don't think it is what people
readily hear
when they hear politics today because
most people
that's too bold many people that i'm in
discussion with
feel that politics is something that
they can have nothing to do with they
can
it can be their life can be basically
free from politics
and they're very suspicious of people
who have a political agenda
so that obviously means that they're not
thinking of politics
in that first definition because the the
first thing you talk about they can't
escape from there is no place where you
can get free from
distributed cognition and that's
aristotle's point
or culture um so given that you have
these two definitions do you prefer the
ancient one
over the more modern one are you trying
to negotiate a relationship between them
in your proposal
i you know looking at people with those
two attitudes let's say about politics
um i've got kind of three opinions i
think the first opinion that's really
pertinent to us
is people might just not see how the
skills that apply to the domains they
are
interested in also apply to the
political domain am i just not
seeing that connection i do think
there's a lot of people who
have this sort of the negative affect
and distanced
relationship to politics as if it was
the domain of some other
and i th that that's a political problem
in the organization of the culture
is that we disown our relationship to
the political
well we see it as a viable intelligence
that we can cultivate and that may be
one of the reasons we're not getting
very far politically is that most people
have opted out
emotionally from that domain yes but we
can
you know we can say what is politics but
we can also say what should it be what
would we like it to be
right right in my mind the goal is
something like a
wisdom civilization right right so i'm
going to skew all definitions in that
direction
regardless of how viably justified that
is by history
and i'm going to think about that in two
ways and one is
what are this how do we create the
supportive conditions in the culture
partly through the organizing principles
of governance in order to
allow people to flourish in the
direction of wisdom
also what can we do at the structural
systemic level of society that is
analogous to individual wisdom
cultivation procedures
right right so i take it to mean then
that um the
vehicle of these facilitations will not
exclusively be
the state that there are other um
institutions or um
subsystems of the culture that you also
think will be invoked
in this kind of political change that
you're proposing is that correct
yeah i think we need to generalize the
meaning and there are ways in which
everyone already has done that right
everyone knows about office politics
that's not the state right so wherever
there's negotiations between people
about how we get things done that
becomes political because
you have to figure out a principle of
collective decision making and then
enact it that's politics
so you so for you politics is therefore
basically germane
to the collective decision-making that
gives
some kind of government or regulation to
this
to the problem-solving of distributed
cognition is that a fair
that's very fair yes
so that would mean that even two people
having a conversation about where
they're going to
have dinner would in that sense be
political
yes i think that's a i mean that's an
outlier
in terms of most people's feelings about
the subject but i think it's a viable
part of that
and i think it's important to view it
that way
because the more you can see the
opportunities
for how interpersonal decisions can be
made better
the more insight you have into how that
can be deployed
at scale so therefore
is is there a continuum between the
a continuum in the sense of a continuity
of
uh principles uh you know
design principles um between the small
scale
interactions like say like we're doing
right now
and the large scale uh processes of the
state
do you see that it was on a continuum so
that the absolutely yeah
oh i see the simplest and most commonly
pointed out aspect of that continuum is
the parallel between political views and
domestic organization
right everybody from wilhelm wright to
george lakoff has pointed out how the
the way the kids are raised in the
household sets up the metaphorical
structure of how they think the system
should be laid out nationally
and all right so some of those layouts
are smarter than others
some are more flexible than others yeah
there's that and there's some
some interesting empirical data on that
um
trying to determine um sort of people's
political allegiance
if you ask them directly that's not a
good mark but if you ask them about
their attitudes to parenting
those are that's often a very good
predictor of their sort of true
political leanings
um so that so there's what i'm saying is
there's
that metaphor is not just sort of uh a
cultural ornament or a faceless
it seems to point to something of a
predictive relationship
and that would tend to support your
proposal of a continuum
so the reason why i'm asking all of this
is you know is i i generally
i i i generally try not to get involved
with the debates between right and left
uh because i think there are deep
problems
uh on both sides that um
it's similar to the thing i do with
between the realists and the
anti-realists or between the theists and
the atheists
um i tend to find that there's shared
problematic presuppositions on both
sides
that i want to challenge now part of my
understanding is that metamodernism also
wants to challenge those
shared presuppositions so um that's fine
and
i often use and zach stein used the same
term
uh for me i have to talk about um
you know that i'm considered i'm sort of
concerned with the meta
uh political i'm concerned with what are
the what are the conditions of
possibility
for the kinds of collective problem
solving
uh that we need in order to bring about
as you said a wisdom culture
so i think that now that you have
specified and stipulated how you're
using the word political i'm fine with
that because
uh it aligns with um
i mean you can have whatever opinion you
want that's not what i mean what i mean
is i think
we have common ground uh where we can
have this discussion
yeah i um i mean instinctively
i would call myself something like a
meta progressive but i think a meta
frame is necessary no matter what
and there's a couple different ways to
approach that you know
in the integral theory there's a
necessity to unpack stages or
developmental levels
as well as a left right polarization and
then to think of left and right as
something operating at various
nested epistemic levels
so that's one thing and then the meta
perspective
i think one of the things meta-modern
brings in is a much more nuanced
critique
of the underlying metaphysical
assumptions of modernity
which include our standard political
spectrum of left and right
which is opposed to us like it's two
fundamental options
but really that's part of the polarized
operating
procedure of the standard model of the
last few centuries
well that's exactly it i i the way uh
i think you said it very well the um
shared
implicit epistemology and metaphysics of
the so-called left and right um i think
and i
they're you're right they are both born
out of modernity clearly
and deeply and continuously dependent on
that and therefore
uh there are important shared
presuppositions that need to be
challenged there i think that's
essential
i think also a particular recent turn
uh that has exacerbated by social media
that has now
become at least de facto probably not
the juror but a de facto shared
presupposition which is
that we have forgot that the left right
um
was supposed to be a form of opponent
processing a way to facilitate
self-correction
within distributed cognition and that
our ultimate allegiance was
to the distributed cognitions
functionality to the
to the process but that has degenerated
into
a a cultural cognitive grammar of a
zero-sum game
and adversarial processing and winners
and losers and destroying the other side
and
so the whole idea of like the
idea of dewey that you've got a deep
interconnection between the
self-correcting processes of science and
the self-correcting processes
of democracy has been lost the idea that
um your your commitment is always
to the country or at least to the
process
of democracy and science within
distributed cognition
so that's that's a modernist thing to
say i get that
what i'm saying is even that modernist
uh presupposition
is now i think been largely discarded
and we are now
into no self-correction within
distributed cognition is not what this
is about
this is about me winning and you losing
because there's a zero-sum game and i
need to uh
try and hold on to whatever power and
privilege access to the state gives me
yeah there's two ways in which a
trans-modern
critique or trans-modern politics is
necessary
one of them is to say there are inherent
problems within the logic of the modern
apparatus the modern way of organizing
and that that uh homeostatically ensures
its ongoing survival through opponent
processing when it's working well
it keeps itself from changing by having
two apparent directions to go in all the
time
and i think that's not just left and
right politics that's you know the
prosecutor and the defender
and it's the x y axis of the cartesian
grid right down the line with this
polarized
nuke the other side is like you say
even by its own metrics modernity is
failing
to be that and therefore also requires a
trans-modern politics to correct its
collapse
thank you layman you you uh you put
those two together and said that
very well that was very succinct and
very clear thank you for that
so that means we now have a proper
philosophic philosophical problem we can
tackle
which is well what are those two trans
modern
moves or i mean or what are the two
kinds
maybe there are they each form a set of
things two kinds of
uh trans-modern uh political moves you
want to see happen
yeah it's interesting to look at it from
those two angles because though on
on the in terms of modernity's
corruption let's say
yeah in terms of the sub-systems of the
modern civilization
buying with each other and destabilizing
and therefore opening up
the regressive move back to pre-modern
cultural trends
yeah that's come about in the form of
several crises you know you might even
argue
as some people have that every couple of
decades modernity
self-sabotages yeah requires some kind
of progressive political
band-aid like in the new deal for
example
right modernity fails on its own terms
and then has to have a
pseudo socialist facelift right right
right
so there's that sense in which people
might even argue that right that bernie
sanders is the real savior of capitalism
because if you made those european style
upgrades to the social safety net
you'd have a much more flourishing
modern capitalist economy
right right on the other hand
that's going to have inherent
limitations and those inherent
limitations are
you know well critiqued by people for
the last 200 years
right they mainly take the form of
marginalization or
every kind of excluded externality
there's whole population groups we're
not looking at there's
ecological background conditions we're
huge factors in which the gdp does not
indicate how well the economy is doing
exactly exactly
the trans-modern politics in that sense
would be an attempt to
fold in what's currently external to the
modern
metrics right uh so
the the part of that that i have some
understanding of
the parts are um like you said the way
modernity has us
disembeded uh from uh from
history and uh ecology um
uh and people say but his republic is
all about history no
it's not about history again in the
sense of
uh understanding like what heidegger
talks about
an understanding of the cultural
cognitive grammar and how it's been
evolving
um uh modernity suffers from the end of
history
myth that it is the culminating way of
understanding everything
and therefore it doesn't need to pay
attention to previous ways of
understanding
or they and therefore look for new ways
so i think i agree with you
that's what i mean by how it's
disembedded from its history it's
obviously deep
deeply disembedded from um uh the
the ecology and um that that shows up
in multiple ways and then what you said
about
gdp and wealth
and money uh being very poor
metrics for trying to understand human
well-being
and so the implicit assumption is that
they are
the metrics that constitute
the algorithm of the normativity by
which we
judge whether or not we're doing well or
not um yeah i think that's also
something that needs to be seriously
brought into question
so how
sorry i'm sorry i don't mean to back you
into a corner like now layman
solved the world but i mean uh so
how though um yeah i think it's got a
couple of different sides
i think one thing is what we're doing
right now because the question would be
this from
like the religious angle that i try to
bring into it
is why is there why are we missing the
we
that could adequately address the meta
crisis
at the in late modernity right all right
and
so that uh a collective spirit is
missing a nation spirit is missing in
the nations and a more general spirit is
missing more generally
so how do you get that we in order to
make some of these changes because that
seems to have to come first
right you could propose all kinds of
intelligent systemic upgrades
well we need a new voting system right
plurality voting
in a non-proportional sense it's not
really
expressing the will of the people at all
and you're not going to get anywhere
unless you have a smarter voting system
okay but how are we going to make that
change we have to share a common ethos
to make that change
first and you get that common ethos on
the one hand through a small
nucleus of people who are trying to
figure out for themselves
through sense-making engagements what
that new ethos is like
the problem is those people it's too
slow to expect that that will spread to
everyone in time
so those people have to at some point
start to converge on a minimum set of
policy demands
that would raise the bottom uh the floor
of the society
in a way that can piggyback on
spontaneous mass mobilizations of people
around certain issues and themes so
that's where the
meta progressive argument would come in
it's not that we agree with
you know everything that's going on in
the streets in the united states for
example
but we have to be looking at what's
going on in the mass of the people
that we could link into in a way that
this
better sense makers can validate
as a minimum set of changes that would
depressurize stabilize and enhance the
overall system
so that on top of that a much more
sophisticated politics might be able to
evolve
okay so that's very interesting um
maybe at some point we could talk about
that in connection with uh the proposal
i
have about stealing the culture uh but
i'm
i'm interested in
perhaps if you could give a concrete
example
of what um one of these minimally
necessary proposals
uh would look like and and sort of how
does it
because what i see what i see those
needing to do
is they they need to almost be symbolic
in the sense of they need to
they need to have they need to have a
meaning
uh for our current frame um in order for
them to catch
uh but they also need to have they also
need to have a meaning to the emerging
sense-making frame um and so
do you maybe you don't no shame if you
don't i'm not saying
but do you have a concrete example that
we might discuss in detail
well we could think about something like
the um
the the two different types of
progressive
economic well-being proposals that have
gone on in the states and around the
world so
federal jobs guarantee or universal
basic income
right right those are a little bit in
tandem some people lean one way some
people in the other way
a lot of people would like to see some
mix of those two right
the purpose of both of those things is
to create
more economic flow through in a
distributed way in the culture
and more economic security as human
beings which has turned out to be
extremely necessary because inevitable
system shocks are coming
yeah and people do have to be able to at
least temporarily
fall out of their profession and still
have a livelihood
in order for there to be a decrease of
anxiety and tension and in order for
them to still be able to spend into the
economy
and have enough unstressed time to work
on their development practices
so that's the general picture of you
know depressurizing and stabilizing
and in preparation for inevitable
instabilities that are coming
but then the way you would key into the
meta
element of it is to frame it in
something like a maslow's hierarchy of
needs thing
right you don't need everyone to have
the same amount of money
in fact we know that there's a there's
an initial amount
of financial stability that does most of
the well-being work
totally totally it's up for grabs right
you don't need everyone to have a
million dollars
you need everyone in general yeah
basic stability to make them able to
move to the next level of meeting making
so yeah so that's what i was going to
say and so what what
what i see ubi and other things doing is
saying
look when people are in scarcity
mentality
their problem-solving abilities go down
their cognitive flexibility goes down
their ability to pursue long-term goals
goes down in fact
people like margaret thatcher had the
causation the wrong way around
they blamed the poor for you know being
impulsive et cetera
so no it's we have overwhelming evidence
that uh scarcity mentality and it's not
just financial scarcity it's scarcity of
other things
uh scarcity of relationship uh scarcity
of social contact
scarcity healthcare um etc so all kinds
of scarcities
uh basically put people into a very
tight reciprocal narrowing
which really limits uh their ability to
cultivate wisdom but what
so how so this is a there's a point that
comes up when
in discussion with zach it seems to me
that we need to pair
uh these kinds of socioeconomic
uh proposals with something like
sort of pedagogical proposals of some
kind
because here's the concern might be that
right you want to get people out of
scarcity
but you want you want to do so you don't
want to mandate i get that
but you want to do something to afford
people
then using up that liver that liberated
cognitive
ability um at least part of the part of
it should be
or exactly what we're proposing here
which is the cultivation
of wisdom so how do you how do you get
that
it so it that strikes me where some of
the stuff we've been talking about
earlier
uh comes to mind which is a project
that you know the religion that's not
religion the the the
the version you've talked about in
previous conversations it seems like
that
that that is needed to go along and then
here's the concern i have
it sounds to me like that project
has to be also paired and minimally
afforded with
their socioeconomic policies but i'm
very
wary of giving the state access
to the emerging let's just let me use my
term for now please
uh the emerging religion that's not a
religion so that's my concern
so let me just simplify that i'll
summarize
i think that the socioeconomic proposals
need to be prepared
need to be paired with for broadly
speaking spiritual religious proposals
i'm okay with the state over here with
the socioeconomic policy
you know enforcement generation and
enforcement i'm not happy with the state
over here
uh because we've got that's we've got a
very good history
and one of the things that i thought
modernity got right was no no
the state and that and whatever it is
religion
let's not get those really tightly bound
together um
but maybe maybe you want to criticize
that notion
well i think it is important to think
about those as two zones
of inquiry right the uh whether it's the
lower left and lower right on the
integral grid or
something like uh participatory and
procedural
approaches right because there you've
got to build
spirit for the we and you've got to have
correlated procedures to implement that
and those reinforce each other rather
than
destructively interfere with each other
yes yes uh however
uh i think there's a a critique we could
bring to the standard modern notion of
the separation of church and state
please say that what they're doing is
separating the pre-modern notions of
church and state
right when they're doing that
habermassie and separation of the value
spheres
actually setting up a bigger picture in
which a comparable integration could
take place
it looks totalizing and totalitarian in
the pre-modern
sense but that's because that's a
smaller sense so we're going to widen
out the space between those
but that doesn't necessarily mean they
don't end up on the same page
because if we think about uh some of the
great modern figures if you think about
like a benjamin franklin who's almost a
a civic saint in the sense of socrates
or kierkegaard or
goethe or those guys right he seems to
bring
a religiousness to his political affairs
and to the orchestration of the saint
it seems to be sort of harmonized and
smoothed out
in that embodiment and i think there are
modern figures and there are modern
moments in which that tends to occur
and that's sort of the idealized version
of how modernity could operate
the opposite of modernity subsystems all
disagreeing with each other
would be modernity subsystems
orchestrated together to create the kind
of surplus harmony i keep talking about
and that could happen with modernity
we'd like it to happen with a
trans-modern system
but that system's just in the process of
booting up
so i think it's not so much that the
church and state gets separated
it's that lower versions of church and
state get separated
so that something religion like can
flourish at the next level
but we might not call that religion you
might just call it a generalized
spirit of you know shared culture and
coherence or something like that
stephen batcher calls it a culture of
awakening which i
which i think is a way of putting it
yeah
i treat the word renaissance and the
word religionization
as kind of convergent when when they're
happening
correctly or healthily in my terms
yeah so i mean this this means like i
mean
this i think points towards sort of a
meta-modern understanding
of what religion would be like um that
it's
it's going to be inherently pluralistic
not relativistic but it's going to be
sort of inherently pluralistic
at one level perhaps at the
propositional level while being
well also tied to more universal
processes
by which people access and accentuate
religio
um and i i sort of see that as
part of what i want what i'm trying to
talk about when i'm talking about an
ecology of practice
and i i keep repeating i keep reminding
people even in the
sangha that i lead but you're not the
idea is not that we all do all the same
practices is that we
get an idea about what are areas what
are types of practices
right um and what are principles or how
types of practices can be linked and
layered
and put into opponent processing
complementarity
and all of that and then but people
would still be i mean
they should be free to choose like maybe
my practices are going to come primarily
from christianity
or perhaps they're going to come from
you know aspects of christianity and
buddhism or
et cetera et cetera does that sort of
line up with what you're proposing
well absolutely i mean if you try to
imagine to extrapolate what a
trans-modern
system looks like it's got roughly all
the benefits of modernity but it's much
more multifarious it's much more
realistic it's also much more ecological
so the term ecology of practices is good
not just because it speaks to a shared
pool
from which we intentionally or
instinctively draw the practices that
we're using at any given time
but also because i think we can guess
that the ecosystem is going to be a much
bigger
part of that new religionization than it
has been in the past
at least since the uh archaic era yeah
i agree with that i agree with that so
the idea would be
that i mean that would bring us closer
to aristotle's notion and even perhaps
plato's notion
i'm not talking about his specific
political proposals like the philosopher
kings
um although marcus aurelius uh does come
to mind as
a clear success um
but the idea that um sort of analogous
to how
philosophia the cultivation of wisdom
and the and the practice of politics
were supposed to be wed together
you're seeing something like sort of
wise uh
religiosity not sorry right
and and political practice being uh wed
together
absolutely i think um you know where
you've seen really uh bold historical
examples of religion
whether it's islamic or tibetan buddhism
or the catholic church
you see that they exert a kind of supra
political political influence
yeah well they're civilization builders
yeah well they're in their flourishing
moments as opposed to their decay
moments
yeah yeah um they're stepping across the
normal
genres of business and politics and
orchestrating together
people in a shared symbol language a
shared spirit
a shared sense of a transcendent
something on behalf of which
they could be mobilized to make changes
that meet their current moments
because one of the things we face now is
everyone agrees there's a crisis
there's actually a lot of agreement on
what the solutions might look like
but mobilizing individuals and
mobilizing systems to do anything about
that
seems to be a real problem we lack the
sense of energy and clarity and
coherence and that we could actually
accomplish something that part
in a way the religious part the spirit
is missing
i agree with you on that um so here
here's a uh you know
some distance between you and i though
um and
maybe i'm pretty sure we'll be able to
close the distance
i i tend to be more pessimistic and uh
and therefore more radical
and that's why i have the proposal of
steal the culture and i
often say i don't want the french
revolution i want something like the axo
revolution
i want what christianity did right it
basically
underneath and even under oppression uh
uh
like it built a a new culture a new way
of being
that then permeated up and then uh took
the
stole the stole the roman empire from
existing power structures and basically
uh
built the grammar for um
the new civilization the medieval world
and that's what i mean by stealing the
culture that kind of thing
because i was just at the movement
summit
uh a week ago yesterday and just the
number of communities of practice
in which people are not just talking
they're doing all these transformative
practices
movement practices mindfulness practices
discourse practices and they're
integrating these ecologies and it's all
happening and they're all getting
starting to get together and network and
talk and so i want to facilitate that as
much as possible
and where i think i might be more
pessimistic to you but i i respect you
so i want to hear
i'm open to being persuaded by you um i
i mean i come from sort of a chomsky in
view that the game is so badly rigged
now the game is so badly rated you know
and jordan hall has had an influence on
me on this too
the game is so badly rigged um
and even the social media like
it's so badly rigged in to perpetuate
and you alluded to this earlier
to perpetuate a very decadent uh
modernity
meaning crisis oppositional um
vicious in the sense of vice and also
cruel form of capitalism um
that i'm i i don't know if we can work
within the game
enough uh to bring about the changes
well i think that that's one of the
areas where we have to work
right then we need to think of an
ongoing struggle that never has an end
and is constantly applied in multiple
silos
let's say right right right that you're
you've all got to work
within the system you've always got to
be building counter institutions to the
system
uh you've always got to be building up
the spirit of the base
you've always got to be looking for
top-down leverage points that will
facilitate all of those things
so it's a multi-front battle so to speak
if we're
you know can tolerate the battle
metaphor uh and there are
i mean it is very uh exciting to be
among people
and see the flourishing of new
communities of practice and inquiry
there are some limitations on that one
is can that spread fast enough to meet
the
impending crises another one is does
that spirit
translate into protocols that are as or
more effective than the current
protocols and can out compete them
yes and then the third one is what if
you got
95 of people in the new category and the
remaining five percent was a tiny little
self-sustaining loop that still exerted
all the military and technological and
media control
right right so that you've got to get in
there and we know from
for example the covet thing the
different response patterns of different
countries
at the state level have made a huge
difference in the
well-being state so you've got to get
into that top-down structure
as well as build alternative
institutions as well as
steal the culture and grassroots
uprising
well that that was well said and i
i think that i i i intend honestly to
take it very seriously
um like i guess it comes to a question
about um
i mean the urgency of this we both share
a sense
of the urgency of the situation in fact
you're you're you're
you're you're you're taking that as a as
a given premise
upon which you're making many of your
arguments um
and and i think the the urgency and this
is an idea i get from jordan right
the urgency is even more urgent than we
realized because
uh the rate of change is itself changing
right things are getting complex
even faster right so um it's going up in
a non-linear
uh progression
and so i have serious questions about
let me give you a concrete example of
what i mean yeah
madison and the other founding fathers
of the united states depended on the
fact that the country was
physically large that was that was they
they were
relying on that as a background
constraint
to prevent kind of mass hysteria
and mob politics because they were very
worried they knew enough from the
ancient world athens etc
that democracy can degenerate very fast
into something like that
so they were very dependent on that and
then they framed the institutions around
that
right uh and the checks and balances
the problem is that that is now from
it has gone from being a governing
variable
to being completely irrelevant because
of social media largely irrelevant
and then the checks and balances that
were supposed to work within a certain
timing of events that was constrained by
the physical space of the country
no longer work and then you get gridlock
and you get adversarial processing
so i don't know if
the machinery is set up
to the kind of environment that we're in
right now
i think there's a lot of truth to that
and i think the
the solutions to that are to try to
create alternative machinery
but also to look for any openings to
hack the system in the right direction
right and also there's the fundamental
human existential position the whole
time which is
you don't know if it's going to work out
or not i got to live right in the moment
and think that that creates change
because you honestly don't know
at a certain level what creates change
how you got to where you are
how any of the systems got to where they
are so that you have to work on
being present with your being more
intensely
and hope that that contributes to the
future that's the very basic level
but at the same time we are going to be
involved socially
all the time as social beings yes yes
means
setting up new practices setting up new
spirit
but also trying to intervene wherever we
see intervention possibilities
within the existing structure given that
it absolutely is built to prevent change
from happening
nonetheless that doesn't mean it's not
hackable right when donald trump ran for
president in 2016
he did this amazing thing which is he
hacked the media incentive structure
yeah they are in general opposed to him
most of the mainstream media people
but they couldn't resist showing a a
train wreck on the television every time
he said something right
and that ended up with billions of
dollars of free political propaganda
that he didn't have to cover or pay for
at all right he almost became
anti-fragile against the media system
by causing one of its incentives to
fight the other incentive
so there may be all kinds of ways to do
that that people just haven't really
found yet because they haven't been
looking it for them
well i mean yeah and and i think that's
right and i mean
to buttress your argument um when a
system is very destabilized
then you get you get an emergence of
the increased power of sensitive
dependence on initial conditions
small perturbations that otherwise would
be dampened down by the inertia of the
system
now actually have a viable chance of
having a larger causal impact
we're at 99 degrees doesn't take much to
bump it to boil or
or be fluid right exactly exactly
exactly
so i i get that but then
so sorry this is not meant to be sort of
a machiavellian argument
the point is i sort of have this
argument that goes something like this
if we're at a place where the individual
actions might make a difference
that is where the system is very
significantly destabilized
and then a real possibility of that is
that the system is
actually going to it's actually going to
collapse
so
how can we tell i mean i get your point
your point is you know all the
historical analogies are sort of off
because we're actually ignorant because
of the situation we're in
but how do we know we're not sort of at
the equivalent of rome
uh you know 376 where you know or even
at the time of dictation
right he he does he does these huge
you know attempts to reform the empire
and all they do is uh uh after he dies
they just generate civil war
that further weakens the empire and
basically the western empire is just
then doomed
right um so
well i i think in a lot of ways it
doesn't matter
right because you don't know the
struggle to make things better is an
endless struggle and it doesn't matter
what moment you're in
there's always possibilities until
there's no possibilities right
we can't go well we i guess we shouldn't
really try because we might be in a
moment where
it won't work yeah so that's a morally
self-sabotaging argument so what we need
is the moral
character as the great moral leaders
have had throat history
to go forward with the fight regardless
of the analysis
of the moment to some degree and there's
always i think leverage points right the
uh
the time of the so-called five good
emperors right rome was on decline
until one of the guys didn't have kids
and decided the new process would be i
hire and train an apprentice
yeah exactly the fortunes of the empire
started going up again because you
weren't just handing it off to your kid
and assuming he'd be a good emperor and
that was just a that was one procedural
change
but it it turned what could have been
the empire's collapse into the empire's
resurgence
yeah and it culminates in marcus
aurelius who unfortunately was straight
and that had commodus um you know i
agree with you i mean
i have come to the same conclusion uh i
i am very unsure about the causal
efficacy
of what i'm trying to do uh but and so
and then i and then i i have the same
sort of moral argument that you do well
there is no alternative we have to try
we have to try our best
um but i also i also say that
even if there's a way in which those two
arguments can come together
even if i fail causally
it doesn't mean that it's going to be a
complete failure and that's what i think
of people like
augustine and others that they right
they they gather enough
of the candles of culture and
civilization
and a new way of being in a new religion
together uh so that
something survives uh throughout the
collapse
and it actually affords a new
civilization being born
so i i i think
we the reason why i want a little bit
more
than just the moral argument is i i
personally found that
um and i consider myself somebody who's
often very strongly motivated by moral
arguments
i found that that has often not
affectively
been sufficient for me uh
because it had
it is the right thing to do but
the sense that even if we don't stave
off
some kind and and i don't want it
because you know it means millions of
people die
that that's that and that's horrible but
even if we can't
forestall that possibility perhaps then
at least we can lay the seeds of
something
that will be grown out of it and
so that also keeps me going personally
yeah i mean i like i was saying it's a
multi-front battle so to speak
right individually we're at different
places
right one place is we don't know maybe
it will fail but maybe we can
lay the seeds for ourselves or for
something else in the future
do that deep spiritual work that is
independent of the historical moment
and hope that that contributes to the
betterment of the future
uh at the same time we can you know
engage in all kinds of social
experiments and practices not knowing if
they will succeed but having a pretty
good idea
of which ones will work better and that
we're not in a situation
here's where i think we often make a
mistake is we think we're in a single
system
and that system's either going to
improve or fail right
but really we're in multiple interactive
systems yeah
modern sense right there's more
primitive operating systems at work in
society
and there's more advanced operating
systems at work they're interpenetrating
and any one of them could gain the upper
hand or
you know get a 10 boost under any given
conditions
those conditions involve doing practices
and gaining clarity
personally and interpersonally about
which
um specific clear things might make a
huge improvement
yeah and also having the classic sangha
relationship of the
the inter-subjective community of people
who are working on their being
i think that's very well said so i like
the way this goes
what i was proposing to you is i i guess
to bring it back to the practicalities
that it might i i like the idea of
you know we we choose specific policies
that are basically wisdom affording both
individually and
and collectively and some of those might
be
socioeconomic like um ubi
uh some of them i i would be
a little bit different like trying to
get people to recommit
uh to an opponent processing model of
distributed cognition
rather than an adversarial one and you
might need those two together
and i think all of that is good but i'm
also wondering if
we need to also decide like we need to
have a repertoire of politic
policy choices between ones that
and i'm proposing a mixture of them ones
that
might bring about the change now and
also ones that were
have a kind of longevity to them that
would see the future
if things ultimately don't succeed yeah
i think we need to
think in the meta sense we need to think
about multiple time scales
yeah but also about these layered
multiple epistemic approaches
and get really clear about what are the
principles that operate at the different
time scales and at the different social
operating systems
yes yes from my point of view one of the
biggest difficulties in meta modern and
integral thinking
is we over identify the epistemic
cultural operating systems with the
stated values of the people who identify
with those systems
and not the deeper analysis of how those
systems actually
behave right that's very well said like
that comes back to what i was saying
how do you figure out the optimal grip
are we using the right categories of
analysis
to understand what the political
situation is
right so this would cash out then for
it sounds to me like this would cash out
uh
to people having kind of a fluid
political in the narrower sense that we
excluded at the beginning of our
conversation
uh having a very sort of having a
a very fluid political allegiance
because it sounds to me
like people would be voting much more in
terms
of policies than they necessarily would
in terms of a particular party
or a particular personality well we've
definitely got to get off the
celebrity and team sports models yeah
that that's so ancient in us
it'll always be there to some degree yes
but we do have to develop a critique of
that that's strong enough to emotionally
free us to think differently about our
political allegiances and
i think you're right they're going to
have to be more nuanced and more
flexible going forward
and the more clear you are on the
underlying principles the more leeway
you have to look for where those are
showing up
at the moment that's very good i like
that
i like that that's very good
unfortunately we have a shorter time
today and uh but
that's it let's let's continue
yeah but but i want to cycle back next
time
um more into because you know paul
vanrickly has this wonderful statement
um and it brings out the the these
different senses of the word politics
that we've been
talking about here he says politics is
about the the here
and now where religion is about the
always and maybe we could talk a little
bit more
because obviously you're also shifting
the meaning of politics out of that
comparison
uh but yeah you know we keep we keep
talking about the relationship between
these two
um and i'd like to pick that up and talk
to you more about that
yeah i think the the meta political
skill set that is recollected
by religious uh affordances in the
culture
uh does tell us a lot it tells us about
that other time scale
yeah large degree yeah let's pick that
up next time
wow that's great thank you very much
layman this has been wonderful
i look forward to our next conversation
absolutely it's always a pleasure john
yeah take good care my friend